<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Honours preservation without blood, or, A sober advice to duellists being a compendious tract of the most exquisite nature to appease the sudden fits of fury, which English-spirits have of late been too much subject to, with many cautions how without the loss of reputation, or the least imprint of cowardise, as well the nobility as gentry of this nation may refuse to hazard their lives and fortunes on such mean pretences of vindicating miscalled honour or unmanly gallatry, shewing likewise, into what dangerous inconviences men thrust themselves forward in such cases with as account how such duels prove plain murther, and are contrary to the laws of God and man / written by a well-wisher to both peace and honour.</title>
            <author>Well-wisher to both peace and honour.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2601A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4260</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13469662</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13469662</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99667</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44303)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 790:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Honours preservation without blood, or, A sober advice to duellists being a compendious tract of the most exquisite nature to appease the sudden fits of fury, which English-spirits have of late been too much subject to, with many cautions how without the loss of reputation, or the least imprint of cowardise, as well the nobility as gentry of this nation may refuse to hazard their lives and fortunes on such mean pretences of vindicating miscalled honour or unmanly gallatry, shewing likewise, into what dangerous inconviences men thrust themselves forward in such cases with as account how such duels prove plain murther, and are contrary to the laws of God and man / written by a well-wisher to both peace and honour.</title>
                  <author>Well-wisher to both peace and honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Phillip Brooksby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dueling --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99667:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99667:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Honours Preſervation WITHOUT BLOOD: OR, <hi>A Sober Advice</hi> TO DUELLISTS.</p>
            <p>Being a Compendious Tract of the <hi>moſt</hi> Exquiſite Nature to <hi>Appeaſe</hi> the Sudden Fits of <hi>Fury,</hi> which <hi>ENGLISH-SPIRITS</hi> have of <hi>Late</hi> been too much Subject to.</p>
            <p>With many <hi>Cautions</hi> how without the <hi>Loſs</hi> of <hi>Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> or the leaſt Imprint of <hi>Cowardiſe,</hi> as well the Nobility <hi>as</hi> Gentry of this Nation may Refuſe to Hazard their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> on ſuch mean Pretences of Vindicating a <hi>Miſcalled Honour,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmanly Gallantry:</hi> Shewing likewiſe, into what Dangerous Inconveniencies <hi>MEN</hi> thruſt themſelves forward in ſuch Caſes.</p>
            <p>With an Account how ſuch <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ELS</hi> prove plain <hi>Murther,</hi> and are contrary to the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a Well-wiſher to both</hi> Peace <hi>and</hi> Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Phillip Brooksby,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99667:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99667:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>EPISTLE</hi> TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SOund Judgement <hi>has not</hi> capacitated <hi>me for the</hi> State, <hi>nor has</hi> ſober Learning <hi>qualified me for the</hi> Church: <hi>no, I am not</hi> acute <hi>enough for the</hi> Knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Law, <hi>nor</hi> profound <hi>enough for</hi> the Myſterious Goſpel. <hi>Therefore having (perhaps) unadviſedly run my ſelf into a</hi> little Tract, <hi>that borders upon</hi> Policy <hi>and</hi> Religion, <hi>I have endeavour'd to ſteer my courſe ſo, as that I may not</hi> fall foul <hi>on that</hi> Rock, <hi>nor be</hi> ſwallowed up <hi>in this</hi> Gulph: <hi>For I intend nothing contained in this</hi> Eſſay, <hi>as</hi> counſel <hi>from the</hi> Bar, <hi>or</hi> reproof <hi>from the</hi> Pulpit, <hi>but only as the</hi> Remarques <hi>of a</hi> Moraliſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99667:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If thou expectest an</hi> accompt <hi>of the</hi> motives <hi>that induc'd me to this</hi> Raſhneſs: <hi>know, that being by</hi> Birth <hi>an</hi> Engliſh-man, <hi>and by</hi> Education <hi>an</hi> Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demian, <hi>by the</hi> Affection <hi>I have for my</hi> Country, <hi>and out of the</hi> reſpect <hi>I owe to my</hi> Mother, <hi>the</hi> Univerſity, <hi>I thought my ſelf</hi> obliged (<hi>at leaſt to</hi> endeavour) <hi>not to be a</hi> diſparagement <hi>to either: And ſince it lyes not in my way, to contribute to the</hi> making <hi>of</hi> Combes, <hi>nor</hi> bringing in <hi>of</hi> Honey: <hi>that</hi> I <hi>might</hi> exempt <hi>my ſelf from the</hi> Imputation <hi>of</hi> Drone, I <hi>reſolv'd to buſie my ſelf, though about</hi> nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If this will not ſatisfie thee, but that having</hi> read <hi>ſuch a</hi> Trifle, <hi>thou must full into</hi> great admiration, <hi>and</hi> many queſtions, <hi>ſuch as,</hi> Why ſhould this fellow pretend to Write, <hi>&amp;c. Let all thy</hi> Wonder <hi>ceaſe, and all thy</hi> queſtions <hi>be reſolved in this; That</hi> Few Men, who have not Wit enough to Write well, have judgement enough to diſcern that they Write ill.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99667:3"/>
            <head>An Eſſay of Duelling.</head>
            <p>WHile we conceive <hi>Duelling</hi> as an <hi>Action:</hi> under that <hi>Conception,</hi> we muſt have recourſe to <hi>Circumſtances</hi> for its <hi>Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating Epethets</hi> of <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad:</hi> But theſe are ſo various both in <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Kind,</hi> that it will be very difficult to reduce the <hi>Theſis</hi> to any <hi>certainty,</hi> without muſtering up a <hi>Volume</hi> of Inſtances out of <hi>God's Revenge againſt Murder,</hi> or ſome Book like it; and ſo by the ſeveral <hi>deſcants</hi> upon every <hi>Individual Duel,</hi> to deduce Arguments to prove one general <hi>Aſsertion: (Viz.) That all Duels are unlawful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince I intend a Diſcourſe more <hi>Conciſe,</hi> and (I hope) more to the <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> than that comes to, I deſignedly omit the <hi>Enumeration</hi> of that <hi>long train</hi> of <hi>Circumſtances</hi> which wait on our <hi>Actions:</hi> inſtancing only in the moſt general motive that enduceth men to <hi>Duelling;</hi> which I look upon as the proper <hi>Baſis</hi> on which the ſtreſs of my preſent Diſcourſe ought to rely. This Motive I have generally obſerved to be the <hi>preſervation</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> and look upon it as the <hi>end</hi> (or more properly the <hi>beginning</hi>) of all <hi>Duels;</hi> and is indeed <hi>a very fair mark to aim at:</hi> ſo that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99667:4"/>nothing can redound to the diſparagement of the <hi>Archer,</hi> but his proving ſo <hi>Purblind,</hi> as not rightly to diſtinguiſh between the <hi>reality</hi> and the <hi>reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance;</hi> or ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilful,</hi> as never to come neer the <hi>White.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I am fearful that I ſhall too eaſily make it apper that many <hi>Gentlemen</hi> are very <hi>ſhort-ſighted</hi> in this <hi>Particular;</hi> and that either through the <hi>falſe Vizards</hi> they have put upon <hi>Honour,</hi> or the <hi>unjust eſtimates</hi> they make of it, they often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Fight</hi> for the <hi>ſhadow</hi> inſtead of the <hi>ſubstance,</hi> and (through that <hi>miſtake</hi>) <hi>deſtroy</hi> what they ſo Zealouſly endeavour to <hi>maintain.</hi> A <hi>true Diamond</hi> is indeed a Jewel of Price, but it is Rivalled by <hi>Glaſs</hi> and <hi>Pebbles; Iron</hi> may wear a <hi>ſuperficies</hi> as curiouſly <hi>Engraved</hi> as the <hi>purest Steel,</hi> but it is not ſo familiar and kind to the <hi>Loadſtone: Braſs</hi> may bear the ſame <hi>impreſs</hi> with <hi>Gold,</hi> but it cannot put a <hi>cheat</hi> upon the <hi>Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone:</hi> and as for <hi>Honour,</hi> I Fancy it is as diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable by its <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>genuine marks,</hi> as any of theſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Touchſtone</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> I take to be <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> nothing certainly can be ſo true a <hi>Gage,</hi> or ſo juſt a <hi>Standard</hi> of it, as the <hi>Ethicks:</hi> So
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99667:4"/>that I ſhall adventure to make this general aſſertion: (in ſpight of <hi>Hectors) Viz. That it is impoſsible for a Man to be truly Honourable, who is not truly Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi> And though Men have either careleſly, or induſtriouſly ſuffered that one great <hi>embeliſhment, Magnanimity;</hi> as it were to <hi>Monopolize</hi> all <hi>Vertue,</hi> making a convertible Propoſition of it. <hi>That no man can be Honourable, but he that is Stout:</hi> and again, <hi>That no Man can be Stout, but he muſt be Honourable:</hi> Yet I believe the reſt of the <hi>Moral Vertues</hi> would take it very <hi>unkindly,</hi> ſo to be ſhouldred out of doors, but that they ſee <hi>Magnanimity</hi> ſo groſely abuſed, as it is even by thoſe who pretend to be the greateſt admirers of it. How this <hi>Errour</hi> came to eſcape <hi>Conviction,</hi> I know not, but certainly 'tis the greateſt imaginable; and carries <hi>Pawn</hi> (I am confident) with none but ſuch as <hi>really are,</hi> or however would be <hi>thought Ranck Hectors:</hi> And even <hi>ſuch</hi> quickly find themſelves hugely diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in their ill-grounded hopes: For whatever they purpoſe to themſelves in the midſt of their <hi>huf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing,</hi> yet while they are endevouring to impoſe the name of <hi>Bubble</hi> upon others, they become the greateſt ones themſelves, owing their <hi>Greatneſs</hi> to a <hi>vapour,</hi> till they <hi>break</hi> into <hi>Nothing.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99667:5"/>And after they have convinced the whole World by their <hi>Duels</hi> and <hi>Murders,</hi> what undaunted Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits they have, for which they expect <hi>Adoration</hi> from all that paſs by <hi>them,</hi> they are forced to content <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> with the <hi>applauſes</hi> of two or three of their <hi>Brethren,</hi> and the <hi>ſubmiſsive reſpect</hi> of ſome few of their Creatures: And I make my appeal to any <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>rational</hi> Man, whether a perſon notorious for <hi>Lying,</hi> a Prodigious <hi>Sot,</hi> an abominable <hi>Lecher,</hi> or the like, gain the leaſt <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Eſteem</hi> with any, but ſuch as are like himſelf, though he be the <hi>ſtoutest man living.</hi> For my part, I would no more <hi>eſpouſe</hi> ſuch an acquaintance, becauſe of his <hi>Courage,</hi> than I would chuſe to <hi>Marry a beaſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Strumpet,</hi> becauſe ſhe had a <hi>ſprightly eye,</hi> or ſome other commendable <hi>feature:</hi> and do not find any <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachreſis</hi> in the <hi>Analogy,</hi> more, than that the latter is a companion the leaſt miſchevious and dangerous of the two.</p>
            <p>Thus it is my opinion, that a man who is every way <hi>morally vicious,</hi> excepting in his Courage, ought to live with leſs <hi>Honour,</hi> than he that is in all other reſpects <hi>morrally good,</hi> and well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, though a <hi>Coward,</hi> for <hi>Courage</hi> is the <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and if a man wants it, 'tis not his <hi>fault</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99667:5"/>but his <hi>misfortune: Nature</hi> is <hi>unkind,</hi> and he is <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy;</hi> he is <hi>good</hi> to the uttermoſt of his <hi>Power,</hi> by <hi>ſuppreſsing Nature</hi> when 'tis <hi>rebellious,</hi> but he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>encourage</hi> it when 'tis <hi>faint-hearted:</hi> he finds it <hi>deficient</hi> in his <hi>heart,</hi> and therefore ſupplies that <hi>chaſm</hi> by a more than <hi>common liberality</hi> of his <hi>hands, affabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of his <hi>Tougue,</hi> &amp;c. And ſince he wants one <hi>branch</hi> in the <hi>Tree of Honour,</hi> he ſo orders and diſpoſes of the reſt, that they <hi>flouriſh</hi> to the <hi>making up of that Breach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus while the Gentleman I mentioned even now, makes <hi>neceſsity</hi> of a <hi>Vertue, by preſsing his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to vindicate the Quarrels of his many other vices,</hi> this makes a <hi>vertue of neceſsity,</hi> by <hi>marſhalling all his other excellencies to the concealment of this deformity.</hi> While <hi>he</hi> has <hi>a mind ſo beclouded, as to abate much of the luſture of his Fortitude; This</hi> has a <hi>Soul</hi> ſo <hi>ſerene,</hi> as even <hi>to lend Rays to his Puſillanimity.</hi> While <hi>he Arrests</hi> his <hi>Magnanimity to pay the debts of</hi> his <hi>drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs,</hi> this by his <hi>temperance, plays the good Husband,</hi> and <hi>contracts none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that I intend this for a <hi>Panegyrique</hi> of <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardice,</hi> but only by this <hi>Antitheſis</hi> to evince how groſely they miſtake, who think <hi>all Honour placed in a readineſs to go into the Field upon every the leaſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99667:6"/>and him to be the <hi>only Gentleman,</hi> that will do this, though in all other matters he be <hi>vitiated,</hi> even to a <hi>Debauch.</hi> But taking what I have ſaid for granted, the conſequence will be this: That <hi>Courage</hi> alone cannot <hi>maintain,</hi> much leſs purchaſe <hi>Honour,</hi> unleſs there be a <hi>conſent,</hi> and a <hi>combination</hi> of the <hi>other vertues</hi> to aſſiſt it. Arms look very <hi>naked</hi> without <hi>Suporters:</hi> And let the <hi>Soloeciſm</hi> appear how great ſoever, 'tis a <hi>Truth</hi> that <hi>Affability</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs</hi> is the beſt <hi>varniſh</hi> to <hi>Courage,</hi> which (like <hi>vineger</hi>) will fret and feed upon it ſelf, unleſs it be allayed with <hi>Water,</hi> or ſome more innocent <hi>Liquor.</hi> But the miſchief of it is, that Men are now generally become their own <hi>Heralds,</hi> they will not remember that <hi>Honor est in honorante;</hi> nor be beholding to the World for that <hi>Worſhip,</hi> which they conceive to be a juſt <hi>Debt</hi> to their <hi>Merit.</hi> They grow furious, and are like <hi>Nebuchadnezer:</hi> for putting all men (like <hi>Neba</hi>) to Death that will not <hi>Idolize</hi> theſe <hi>Images</hi> of their own ſetting up. But if theſe would conſider that their <hi>Reputation</hi> lyes in other Mens hands, they would certainly remember that it is rather to be <hi>won</hi> with <hi>gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>civility,</hi> than by <hi>rigor</hi> and <hi>force.</hi> The ſuddain ſnatching of ſo <hi>brittle</hi> a <hi>Mettle</hi> may <hi>crack</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99667:6"/>it, when Care and ſoft uſage may preſerve it <hi>entire.</hi> And the beſt advice that can be given in this caſe, is certainly this: <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Men would be ſo <hi>Ingenious</hi> as to get a <hi>Reputation</hi> before they grow ſo very <hi>Zealous</hi> to keep it.</p>
            <p>But there is a Second ſort of <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> who would take this advice as an <hi>Affront,</hi> becauſe they come not under the <hi>ſcandal</hi> of <hi>Debauchery:</hi> And yet many of theſe are <hi>Peccant</hi> in a more than commendable <hi>forwardneſs</hi> to receive <hi>affronts,</hi> though not ſo ready to give them. Theſe (in their own conceits) have <hi>Honours</hi> of a moſt Prodigious <hi>Magnitude,</hi> and indeed <hi>ſwel'd</hi> to that <hi>Diſproportion,</hi> that it is rather to be feared they are <hi>puft up</hi> with a <hi>Tympany of Pride,</hi> than <hi>conſolidated</hi> with firm <hi>Nobility.</hi> If a Man that has not the <hi>Breeding</hi> of the <hi>Town</hi> come into their Company, 'tis impoſſible he ſhould <hi>live:</hi> Alas! this <hi>dull Animal</hi> cannot breath in their <hi>Aura.</hi> There is <hi>Civility</hi> in its <hi>Purity,</hi> when a Man that does not underſtand himſelf can neither look, ſpeak, nor do any thing but what is taken for an abuſe: If there ariſe any <hi>Diſpute,</hi> he muſt offer nothing in oppoſition, but what muſt be Uſher'd in with a <hi>by your pardon Sir, I think 'tis ſo—.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99667:7"/>And indeed the <hi>ill-bred Gentleman</hi> may gain a <hi>Fortune</hi> in the Country with half the <hi>ceremony</hi> that he muſt here make uſe of to <hi>Arm</hi> himſelf againſt a <hi>Challenge.</hi> I confeſs theſe <hi>clowns</hi> are unhappy in their want of <hi>Education,</hi> and either by their ill <hi>Managery</hi> of their <hi>actions,</hi> or their <hi>fooliſh retorts</hi> in a diſpute, they oftentimes become <hi>rediculous</hi> in <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> and <hi>abuſive</hi> to <hi>others.</hi> But yet methinks an <hi>ingenious Soul</hi> ſhould make theſe <hi>Occurrences</hi> the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of his <hi>Laughter,</hi> rather than of his <hi>Anger.</hi> I would have <hi>Honour</hi> like the <hi>Palm-Tree,</hi> to <hi>riſe and appear vigorous under any weight,</hi> and not like the <hi>Plant</hi> we call <hi>Senſitive,</hi> to <hi>ſhrink in at every little Touch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the two <hi>instances</hi> already mentioned come not fully to my Purpoſe: the <hi>diſparity</hi> is ſuch that it ſeldom proceeds to a <hi>Duel:</hi> For the <hi>Hector</hi> or <hi>Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin,</hi> is one with whom ſcarce any man will <hi>Fight,</hi> and the <hi>Pedant</hi> or <hi>Buffoon,</hi> is one who will ſcarce <hi>Fight</hi> with any Man. The former is uſually Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with, and the latter commonly lets fall the <hi>Suit</hi> before it comes to a <hi>Tryal:</hi> Therefore before you bring the <hi>Man of Honour</hi> upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> you muſt bring him a <hi>Competitour,</hi> one that is a Gentleman, and in all reſpects lays as great a claim to Gallantry as himſelf; when ſuch meet upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99667:7"/>the leaſt ſhadow of an <hi>affront</hi> ariſes a <hi>Quarrel,</hi> which is preſently <hi>ſeconded</hi> with a <hi>Challenge,</hi> and ends in a <hi>Duel,</hi> as if it were impoſſible for theſe <hi>Cocks</hi> of the <hi>Game</hi> to ſee one another without <hi>Animoſity.</hi> If they cannot be happy in a better <hi>occaſion,</hi> the taking of the <hi>Wall</hi> ſhall ſerve the turn, and if either attempts to go next it, his Adverſary ſhall do his beſt to <hi>verifie</hi> the <hi>Proverb,</hi> by endeavouring him to prove him the <hi>weakest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But almoſt daily experience informs us of worſe effects of the <hi>Sword,</hi> than thoſe we hear of in <hi>rencounters,</hi> of which, if we inquire into the <hi>cauſes</hi> and <hi>originals,</hi> we ſhall find them comprized chiefly in three <hi>Heads:</hi> namely, PLAY, WINE and WOMEN. And whoſoever will be at the trouble of keeping a <hi>Diurnal</hi> of the <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions</hi> of <hi>this City,</hi> I dare ſay, ſhall ſcarce need any other <hi>Common-place,</hi> to refer all the <hi>Duels</hi> that have been fought for ſome years paſt, and will be Fought for ſome years to come, than <hi>Theſe.</hi> How frequent (I may ſay conſtant) effects of this Nature do we daily find to be the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conſequences</hi> of <hi>Play? Paſsion</hi> is its <hi>unſeperable Companion,</hi> and if <hi>Fortune</hi> prove ever ſo little <hi>adverſe,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99667:8"/>the <hi>Loſer</hi> takes occaſion to <hi>Quarrel,</hi> not only at <hi>Her,</hi> but the very <hi>perſon ſhe aſsists,</hi> though (perhaps) a <hi>Boſom Friend,</hi> or a <hi>neer Relation.</hi> As if he reſolved to <hi>humour</hi> his <hi>Fortune</hi> with his <hi>Carriage,</hi> and ſcorned to <hi>behave</hi> himſelf <hi>well,</hi> when the <hi>Dice</hi> run <hi>ill:</hi> Every unlucky <hi>throw</hi> puts him into an <hi>Outrage,</hi> and being grown <hi>deſperate</hi> upon the loſs of his <hi>money,</hi> he <hi>Pawns</hi> his <hi>Reaſon:</hi> Then follow the <hi>God-dam-you's,</hi> and <hi>Plague-confound-you's:</hi> Nay, and 'tis much if he give not the <hi>Lye,</hi> or the <hi>Son of a Whore,</hi> nor is it at all to be <hi>admired,</hi> if having broken out into <hi>Prophaneſs,</hi> he keeps not within the <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Civility.</hi> Theſe (I confeſs) are <hi>indignities</hi> not to be endured, and let a Man be never ſo well <hi>Armed</hi> with <hi>Moderation</hi> or <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> yet ſuch <hi>aſsaults</hi> as theſe, preſently make a <hi>breach,</hi> and force him to <hi>Proclaim open War.</hi> So that in effect <hi>Speering</hi>'s <hi>Ordinary</hi> proves the ready way to <hi>Lambs-Conduit;</hi> and a <hi>ſmooth Table</hi> becomes as <hi>fatal</hi> to throw <hi>Dice</hi> upon, as a <hi>Drum-head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is <hi>Wine</hi> a leſs <hi>incendiary</hi> to theſe kind of <hi>Heats</hi> and <hi>Quarrels,</hi> than <hi>Play:</hi> Nay, moſt commonly it is the <hi>firſt mover,</hi> not only of the <hi>remoter Effects,</hi> but alſo of the more <hi>immediate cauſes;</hi> for <hi>Gameing</hi> and <hi>Whoring</hi> would be <hi>meagre</hi> and <hi>diſregarded vices,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they not <hi>pampered up</hi> with <hi>Drinking.</hi> This takes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99667:8"/>away thoſe <hi>Rubs</hi> and <hi>Obſtacles</hi> which <hi>Sobriety</hi> Dictates to our <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and removes thoſe <hi>Boomes,</hi> which a <hi>temperate reſolution</hi> had ſet up as <hi>Guides,</hi> and <hi>non ultra's,</hi> and while we miſs theſe, no wonder if we <hi>run our ſelves a ground:</hi> Every Man when he is <hi>Sober,</hi> knows that to play with <hi>Rooks</hi> and <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates,</hi> is to make <hi>Ducks</hi> and <hi>Drakes</hi> of his <hi>Money,</hi> and yet one <hi>drunken fit</hi> removes all his <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> and then he will <hi>venture himſelf</hi> with any <hi>Fellows,</hi> and <hi>his money</hi> at <hi>any rate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing him ſo <hi>prudently drunk,</hi> as not to be <hi>drawn</hi> into <hi>Play,</hi> 'tis odds; but you find him ſo <hi>fooliſhly Quarrelſom,</hi> as that way to run himſelf into <hi>equal inconveniencies.</hi> Not one in twenty but is ſo <hi>groſely abuſive,</hi> that it is beyond the patience of a <hi>ſtranger</hi> to endure it: Nay, even his moſt <hi>intimate acquaintance</hi> know not where to have him; their good <hi>advice</hi> is <hi>miſconſtrued,</hi> and their <hi>actions</hi> of <hi>friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip miſlikt;</hi> and unleſs they have leſs <hi>wine,</hi> or more <hi>wit</hi> in their <hi>Heads</hi> than he, you may rationally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect one or more of the Company in the literal ſence <hi>Bloody-drunk.</hi> But it may ſo happen that they are <hi>intercepted,</hi> and theſe <hi>Intestine</hi> (I cannot call them <hi>civil</hi>) <hi>Broyls</hi> reconcil'd: Yet the <hi>miſchief</hi> does not commonly end there, they do but like <hi>neighbouring
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99667:9"/>Princes,</hi> who in the heat of <hi>War</hi> make a <hi>League,</hi> and both joyn againſt a <hi>common Enemy.</hi> They cannot walk (or rather reel) the Street without offering an <hi>affront</hi> to every one they meet. The beſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified <hi>Gentleman,</hi> or the <hi>modeſteſt Lady</hi> cannot paſs them without a <hi>Rudeneſs</hi> offered: So that tracing them from the <hi>Tavern</hi> to <hi>Whetſtones-Park,</hi> you will aſſuredly find ſome <hi>drops</hi> of <hi>Blood,</hi> or hear of ſome <hi>work</hi> cut out for the next <hi>Morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then indeed begins a <hi>Tragi-comoedy,</hi> enough to make <hi>Democritus</hi> look <hi>ſerious,</hi> or <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitus laugh:</hi> Were there a thouſand <hi>Craeſsus's,</hi> 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible they ſhould contain themſelves, ſeeing theſe <hi>Aſses mumbling Thiſtles:</hi> One of theſe awakes in <hi>diſcontent,</hi> juſt remembring that he did <hi>challenge</hi> a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and appointed him a place of <hi>meeting,</hi> but has forgotten where: A Second remembers the place, but knows nothing elſe of the <hi>Quarrel,</hi> A third remembers the <hi>Gentleman</hi> to have been moſt groſely abuſed, without any cauſe at all. Well, after this <hi>coucil of war</hi> has debated the thing, and conſulted <hi>their Honours,</hi> the reſult of all is a neceſſity of <hi>Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Thus as the <hi>Pope</hi> proves himſelf <hi>infallible</hi> by maintaining the <hi>Errours</hi> he runs into: ſo theſe <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen juſtifie</hi> all their <hi>actions</hi> to be <hi>Honourable</hi> by <hi>vindicating</hi> thoſe that are <hi>otherwiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99667:9"/>
            <p>And now I am to beg pardon of the <hi>Ladys</hi> for <hi>ſhouldring</hi> them into any concern in this <hi>Tragedy:</hi> How they came to be engaged, I know not, but according to my obſervation, they are rather the <hi>occaſions</hi> of it, than <hi>actors</hi> in it. We have a <hi>ſaying,</hi> that <hi>there is ſeldom any miſchief done, but a woman is at one end of it.</hi> But in this caſe, the <hi>miſchief</hi> proceeds moſt commanly from our <hi>fooliſh zeal,</hi> not from their <hi>inſtigations.</hi> I conceive the <hi>Precedence</hi> due to thoſe that are <hi>honourable,</hi> and therefore I ſhall firſt <hi>inſtance</hi> in them; ſuch (I mean) as have preſerved their <hi>reputations,</hi> and are eſteemed <hi>Vertuous:</hi> and certainly no ſuch perſon can be thought <hi>acceſsary</hi> to our <hi>follies,</hi> or a <hi>fomentour</hi> of our <hi>vices,</hi> but it (as the <hi>Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> calls it) <hi>cauſa per accidens,</hi> as in this caſe.</p>
            <p>Suppoſing a <hi>Lady Young, Rich,</hi> and <hi>Handſom,</hi> having done that, you ſuppoſe her ſurrounded with <hi>Servants,</hi> of whom poſſibly ſhe <hi>Affects one more Peculiarly,</hi> and he that is thus <hi>happy</hi> or <hi>unfortunate,</hi> (call it which you pleaſe) muſt either <hi>Relinquiſh</hi> his <hi>hopes,</hi> or <hi>Maintain</hi> them with his <hi>Sword.</hi> If he be <hi>Victorious</hi> in the firſt <hi>Encounter,</hi> he ſhall meet with a Second, and if there be Twenty of theſe <hi>Rivals,</hi> they ſhall have the <hi>Fate</hi> of <hi>Red breasts, ſhut</hi> up in an <hi>Aviary:</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99667:10"/>all muſt dye ſave one, and none muſt enjoy this <hi>Venus,</hi> but the <hi>God of War:</hi> While each has ſet up a reſolution not to deſire her <hi>Affection,</hi> but <hi>win</hi> it; which to effect, they propoſe no other way, than by <hi>deſtroying</hi> the <hi>object</hi> of it: and yet this goes for a piece of <hi>Gallantry,</hi> not only <hi>Justifiable,</hi> but <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious:</hi> ſuch an example of <hi>Knight-Errantry,</hi> as that a Man cannot prove himſelf a <hi>Gentleman</hi> without it. I confeſs I admire Actions of this Nature, as much as any Man, but it is for the <hi>raſhneſs</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> of them: for I cannot fancy they have any <hi>rational aim</hi> or <hi>deſign.</hi> Do men hereby propoſe to themſelves enjoyment of the <hi>Lady?</hi> To me it ſeems very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable that ſuch a <hi>woman</hi> as we have already ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, ſhould love a Man for no other reaſon but that he has <hi>Murthered</hi> him ſhe formerly inclined to: or to reward the <hi>improvident Husband</hi> with the <hi>Grapes,</hi> becauſe ſhe chatcht him cutting down the <hi>ſupporters</hi> of the <hi>Vine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But allowing this to be well received on the <hi>Ladies</hi> part, there remains yet another difficulty to be removed before it can proceed to a <hi>Sack-poſset:</hi> there is a <hi>place <hi>night</hi> Newgate,</hi> and a <hi>Creature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eped,</hi> a <hi>Judge,</hi> that will have ſomething to ſay to Mr. <hi>Bridegroom, in Potentia,</hi> who perhaps forbids
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99667:10"/>the <hi>Banns,</hi> and ſo deprives him of the opportunity of being called <hi>handſom Man,</hi> as he is going to <hi>Church,</hi> but gives him as fair a one as he is going to the <hi>Gallows.</hi> Thus falls this <hi>Champion</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> a <hi>Martyr</hi> to <hi>Love,</hi> and he that fancied himſelf to live with all <hi>Imaginable eſteem,</hi> and <hi>repute,</hi> now dyes with <hi>unconceiveable reproach</hi> and <hi>diſgrace,</hi> confeſſing that
<q>
                  <l>Honour <hi>in</hi> Youth <hi>is but an itch o'th' blood,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of doing things extravangantly good.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, I confeſs, of all inſtances this laſt, as 'tis the moſt excuſable in it <hi>ſelf,</hi> ſo 'tis the leaſt <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable</hi> in the <hi>conſequences</hi> of it: becauſe he that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers is a <hi>ſingle perſon,</hi> and <hi>pays</hi> no <hi>debts</hi> but thoſe of his own <hi>contracting:</hi> whereas in ſome caſes, though the <hi>Halter</hi> puts an end to a Mans <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> together, yet the <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> ſurvives to his Poſterity (if he has any.) 'Tis poſſible the <hi>Pendant Gentleman</hi> may leave a Widow and Orphans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing his Diſhonour, and their own Misfortune: for while he makes a <hi>forfiture</hi> of his <hi>eſtate</hi> to the King, and his <hi>good Name</hi> to the <hi>VVorld,</hi> he Entails upon them nothing but <hi>Scandal</hi> and <hi>Beggery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As theſe Diſaſters therefore are not always oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by <hi>Civil</hi> WOMEN, ſo neither are they always the <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>Love:</hi> For if a Gentleman be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99667:11"/>handing a Lady along the Street (whatever ſhe be) how <hi>unmercifully ſtout</hi> does he grow upon a ſuddain, a Man cannot paſs by this <hi>ſhrine,</hi> but he muſt do it <hi>reverence,</hi> at leaſt by keeping a <hi>fit diſtance,</hi> if caſually he gives her the leaſt <hi>justle,</hi> 'tis ten to one but this <hi>zealous Gallant,</hi> out of an <hi>ambition</hi> to <hi>ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate</hi> himſelf, and appear a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>mettle,</hi> comes out with his <hi>Damme what d'ee mean?</hi> or <hi>how now Logger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, what's that for?</hi> and either he draws himſelf, or gives the other provocation enough to do it. Is not this the <hi>Mode</hi> of the <hi>Town?</hi> and do not ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral occurrences like theſe happen in a Year? Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that many times men loſe their lives in vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the <hi>reputation</hi> of a <hi>common Whore,</hi> as if <hi>Honour</hi> (by a kind of <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi>) were to be maintained by things <hi>diſhonourable,</hi> or (like the <hi>Fig-tree) did flouriſh beſt,</hi> when planted near to <hi>Rue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having <hi>traced</hi> theſe <hi>disturbed</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant ſtreams</hi> through all their <hi>by-paths,</hi> and <hi>Moeanders,</hi> from their ſeveral <hi>ſpring-heads,</hi> down to the <hi>Red-Sea,</hi> whether they all tend. I think it time to caſt an eye toward the <hi>Mountain tops:</hi> Thoſe (I mean) of the <hi>Nobility</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentry,</hi> who either by their <hi>Valour</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> are grown to a <hi>greatneſs</hi> and <hi>height</hi> above the <hi>level</hi> of other men. To whom I intend
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99667:11"/>not to be ſo unjuſt, as to endeavour to <hi>raze</hi> or <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> thoſe <hi>Pyramids,</hi> which either their <hi>Anceſtours</hi> or <hi>themſelves</hi> have erected as perpetual <hi>Memorials</hi> of their <hi>Honour.</hi> And indeed, could I be ſo <hi>malicious,</hi> or <hi>daring,</hi> to attempt this, how ſtrangely would my endeavours be intercepted, when our <hi>Engliſh Noble-men,</hi> like thoſe of <hi>Troy,</hi> put forth their <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting hand,</hi> to their <hi>own deſtruction,</hi> and themſelves become inſtrumental to the <hi>Demolliſhing</hi> of their own <hi>Babel?</hi> If two of theſe <hi>Structures</hi> ſtand neer together, lifting up their <hi>heads</hi> of equal height, what <hi>aemulation</hi> and <hi>envy</hi> does it beget, <hi>one</hi> muſt be <hi>pulled down,</hi> e're the <hi>other</hi> can be thought throughly <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed?</hi> as if the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> could be well built upon nothing but its <hi>own ruines:</hi> or like the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol,</hi> it could not be <hi>firmly founded,</hi> but where the <hi>builders</hi> find a <hi>dead Mans skul.</hi> So that if you take a ſtrickt Survey of any of theſe, you will find the Walls <hi>graced</hi> (as they call it) with <hi>ſeveral Hic jacet's;</hi> of which kind of <hi>Monuments,</hi> the more there are, the more <hi>beautiful</hi> and <hi>gorgeous</hi> is the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> eſteemed. Thus do they make <hi>Honour</hi> a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal,</hi> or <hi>Horſleach,</hi> hungry for want of <hi>Mans fleſh,</hi> and thirſting after <hi>blood;</hi> and intimate to the World that there is a <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> ſo incenſed, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99667:12"/>nothing will apeaſe him but <hi>Human Sacrifice,</hi> and that his <hi>Votaries</hi> muſt <hi>offer</hi> nothing at his <hi>Altar,</hi> but like the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Baal,</hi> with the <hi>dreadful Cerimony</hi> of <hi>Cutting</hi> and <hi>Wounding.</hi> This kind of <hi>Religion</hi> I dare not <hi>contradict</hi> or <hi>reprove,</hi> it being the <hi>conſtant reſolve</hi> of the <hi>Matureſt deliberations,</hi> to attempt <hi>Achieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of this <hi>Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>ſtoutest Champions,</hi> to be bleſt in theſe their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, with a <hi>Proſperous ſucceſs,</hi> of whom he is the moſt <hi>Honourable</hi> that has the moſt <hi>Gules</hi> in his <hi>Eſcutcheon,</hi> and the moſt happy that has <hi>enroll'd</hi> the greateſt number of <hi>Martyrs</hi> in the <hi>Kalender</hi> of <hi>Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, for ought I know, may not be an <hi>errour</hi> in <hi>Planets</hi> of the <hi>Superiour Orbs:</hi> but ſure I am, it begets one in the <hi>inferiour</hi> and <hi>ſublunary bodies,</hi> who while they look upon theſe as <hi>true lights,</hi> and <hi>ſafe guides,</hi> find themſelves (as by an <hi>Ignis fatuus) benight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and <hi>ſeduced.</hi> Noblemen cannot but diſcern how Gentlemen of <hi>leſs quality throng</hi> and <hi>croud</hi> to come as <hi>neer</hi> them as is poſſible, imitating them according to (nay beyond) their <hi>Abilities,</hi> in their <hi>Habit, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> and all pieces of <hi>Gallantry:</hi> Nay, even in their <hi>Vices;</hi> eſteeming all things <hi>Lawful,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>Creditable</hi> which are worthy of their purſuit. And
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99667:12"/>were it not an eaſie matter for them to bring this fooliſh and raſh way of <hi>Duelling</hi> into contempt, by being neither <hi>examples</hi> nor <hi>countenancers</hi> of it?</p>
            <p>It would be <hi>Arogance</hi> in me, to propoſe any way for the effecting of this, but my confidence of the Facility of it is (I believe) well grounded, for all Men know, that whoſoever kills a Man in a <hi>Duel,</hi> is <hi>Ipſo Facto,</hi> to be put to death by the <hi>Law,</hi> and yet the <hi>Fountain</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> and the <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> are one and the ſame <hi>Perſon: (Viz.)</hi> The <hi>King:</hi> whom we muſt Accriminate with abſurd and incongruous <hi>contradictions</hi> in his <hi>actions,</hi> if we ſuppoſe him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Honour</hi> upon a <hi>Perſon,</hi> and then immediately make ſuch Laws, which if he obeys 'tis poſſible for him to preſerve. Were there no other means to be uſed for the <hi>preſervation</hi> of a Man's <hi>Honour,</hi> but to <hi>Duel</hi> the perſon that <hi>aſsaulted</hi> it, is it to be imagined that there would ever have been ſo ſevere a <hi>Law</hi> againſt <hi>Duelling?</hi> ſo then, the neceſſity of <hi>Fighting</hi> muſt be <hi>removed,</hi> or the <hi>incongruity allowed,</hi> which would be flat <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Man is <hi>dub'd Knight Banneret</hi> in the <hi>Field,</hi> for ſome <hi>ſignal</hi> piece of <hi>Service;</hi> is this <hi>perſon</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obliged to <hi>challenge</hi> every <hi>Hot-headed Boy,</hi> that ſhall call him <hi>Coward</hi> at home? or may he not by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99667:13"/>a <hi>Sober</hi> and <hi>Prudent carriage</hi> maintain his <hi>Honour</hi> without it: and order it ſo, that the <hi>Pert Youth</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear a <hi>Ridiculous Child,</hi> while he proves himſelf as <hi>Prudent</hi> as <hi>Stout.</hi> And have we not many <hi>gallant examples</hi> of this temper in the Kingdom? Are there not Men of unqueſtioned <hi>Valour,</hi> who have made the <hi>Enemy</hi> confeſs them to be <hi>Lyons,</hi> and yet will ſuffer theſe wanton <hi>Kids</hi> to leap into their very <hi>mouths</hi> without harm? By which means (I think) they rather confirm themſelves to be <hi>true bred,</hi> than give any man occaſion to ſuppoſe them <hi>degenerate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (I fancy) I have but one ſort of Men left to deal with: <hi>(viz.)</hi> Thoſe that allow <hi>Duels</hi> to be <hi>unlawful,</hi> and conſequently <hi>diſhonourable;</hi> and yet out of a <hi>vain glorious humour</hi> will venture at all, reſolving to purchaſe the Name of <hi>Man,</hi> though with the <hi>Epethets</hi> of <hi>fooliſh</hi> or <hi>miſerable.</hi> Yet I am of an opinion, that if the good Laws provided in this caſe were duly executed, much of this <hi>fool-hardineſs</hi> would be abated. But I can never hope to convince one by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> whom the <hi>remiſsneſs</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> or <hi>abundance</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> has thus emboldned: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will try (if he be not above <hi>Fear</hi>) to deter him, by ſetting before him the <hi>unequal terms</hi> upon which he muſt ſometimes <hi>fight.</hi> This <hi>Catholique Dueller</hi> muſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99667:13"/>be ſuppoſed to maintain his <hi>Honour</hi> in all places, and with all perſons: If ſo, than fancying him to be ſmall in <hi>ſtature,</hi> or to have any <hi>natural defect,</hi> or <hi>impediment</hi> whereby he is rendred uncapable of bearing up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one every way compleat, is it probable that ſuch a one ſhould be <hi>Victorious?</hi> So that this poor <hi>Lamb</hi> goes into the field but as a <hi>victim</hi> to <hi>Honour,</hi> and dies with double diſadvantage to be firſt <hi>abuſed,</hi> and afterwards <hi>killed</hi> for it: and all the benefit that he reaps by it, is the <hi>Encomium</hi> of <hi>pretty mettl'd fellow,</hi> and the <hi>Elegy, of a thouſand pitties.</hi> Thus does he gain <hi>compaſsion</hi> inſtead of <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Fools Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice</hi> inſtead of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though Probability gives this <hi>Gyant</hi> the <hi>Victory,</hi> yet 'tis poſſible that <hi>Fortune</hi> may ſo guide the <hi>Pigmy's</hi> ſword, that it may reach the heart of this <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> who upon ſuch an accident, falls with all <hi>imaginable diſgrace;</hi> ſo that in an <hi>unequal Duel</hi> 'tis almoſt impoſſible for either of the <hi>Sword-men</hi> to obtain even that which the <hi>vauntingest huff</hi> miſcalls <hi>Honour;</hi> for in the <hi>first inſtance</hi> the <hi>infirmities</hi> of the <hi>Enemy</hi> are traduced as <hi>blots</hi> in the <hi>Eſcucheon</hi> of the <hi>Victor,</hi> and in the laſt, the Conqueſt is wholly <hi>aſcribed</hi> to <hi>Chance:</hi> and therefore I approve of the anſwer given by a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a great Impediment in his Eyes, deſired
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99667:14"/>his <hi>Antagoniſt</hi> (who Challenged him at <hi>Rapier</hi>) to meet him in a <hi>dark Cellar</hi> with a <hi>Hatchet:</hi> But fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying all deſired <hi>Parity,</hi> perſons equal in <hi>Strength, Skill,</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> how Caſual then is the Event! Certainly in ſuch a caſe the <hi>Victor</hi> muſt allow him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf indebted to <hi>Fortune</hi> for his <hi>Succeſs,</hi> becauſe (as I ſaid) there is an equallity. Might not ſuch <hi>Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoes</hi> as theſe, be perſwaded upon a <hi>mutual affront,</hi> to <hi>draw cuts</hi> for their lives, agreeing that he who drew the ſhorteſt ſhould <hi>hang himſelf</hi> to give the other <hi>ſatisfaction?</hi> Why not? For the <hi>prudence</hi> of this way 'tis certainly the beſt, becauſe the <hi>equallest,</hi> having its whole dependance upon a <hi>caſualty;</hi> whereas in a <hi>Duel</hi> one of the <hi>Combatants</hi> may have the advantage of <hi>skill.</hi> For the <hi>mettle</hi> of it, 'tis the ſtouteſt, becauſe one of them muſt aſſuredly <hi>dye;</hi> whereas in a <hi>Duel</hi> a <hi>Coward</hi> may encourage himſelf with the hopes of being <hi>diſarmed,</hi> or <hi>lightly wounded:</hi> For the <hi>mercy</hi> of it, 'tis the moſt commendable; for here only one periſheth, whereas in a <hi>Duel</hi> both may be <hi>ſlain,</hi> or <hi>deſperately hurt:</hi> For the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of it, 'tis the <hi>compleateſt;</hi> for here a Man has <hi>Plenary Reſtitution,</hi> made by the <hi>Offenders</hi> own <hi>hands,</hi> while he lives at peace and liberty, to enjoy the <hi>happineſs:</hi> whereas in a <hi>Duel,</hi> though he does kill his Adverſary, yet the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99667:14"/>
               <hi>Laws</hi> call a Man into queſtion, and perhaps take away his Life: For the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of it, 'tis (without doubt) the moſt <hi>ticking;</hi> for here you may pleaſe your ſelf with ſeeing your <hi>Enemy</hi> do <hi>Execution</hi> artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially upon himſelf, whilſt you ſtand by as a <hi>ſafe Spectator:</hi> whereas in a <hi>Duel</hi> the <hi>danger</hi> much abates of the <hi>Lechery:</hi> And laſtly, for the <hi>Honour</hi> of it, 'tis far the <hi>greateſt:</hi> for here the <hi>vanquiſht</hi> is but <hi>hang'd:</hi> and that only in ſight of two or three <hi>Friends</hi> (perhaps:) whereas in a <hi>Duel,</hi> the <hi>conquerour</hi> many times ſuffers a more <hi>ignominious death,</hi> even among <hi>Malefactors,</hi> and before thouſands of <hi>beholders.</hi> What a <hi>Ridiculous Soloeciſm</hi> in Morrals is <hi>Duelling!</hi> when even ſo <hi>Bruitiſh</hi> a <hi>propoſition</hi> as this, ſhould appear far more <hi>Rational</hi> and <hi>Eligible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there is one thing yet behind, which hugely agravates the indiſcretion of it, that indeed whereby the name of <hi>Folly</hi> is ſwallowed up in madneſs: That is the uſe of <hi>Seconds.</hi> How this cuſtome crept into the World, I cannot tell, but to me it ſeems the moſt <hi>abſurd</hi> that can be thought of: I am not ſo well verſed in Martial Hiſtory, as to give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Original</hi> of theſe. But ſure I am, if they were intended for good, their Deſign is ſtrangely perverted: Were they <hi>Spectatours</hi> only to ſee that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99667:15"/>no <hi>Foul play</hi> (as they call it) be offered: or ſuch as might be <hi>aſsiſtant,</hi> as <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> it were tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But as they are now uſed, 'tis a <hi>Frenzy</hi> not to be <hi>Parallel'd.</hi> I need not inform the compleat <hi>Dueller</hi> that the <hi>Mode</hi> now adays, is for all the <hi>Seconds</hi> to draw at once with the <hi>Principal;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them the <hi>Engagement</hi> is as <hi>vigorous</hi> as if each were the very perſon that firſt gave the affront. This indeed is <hi>Honour</hi> in it's <hi>purity!</hi> wherein the moſt <hi>curious eye</hi> cannot <hi>diſcern</hi> the leaſt <hi>dregs:</hi> this is that <hi>excellently refined Mettal,</hi> which will endure the niceſt touch of the choiceſt <hi>Loadſtone!</hi> The <hi>Principal</hi> may be encouraged by <hi>Paſsion,</hi> or animated by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,</hi> but here's he that will <hi>fight</hi> with any man in the quarrel of a <hi>Friend;</hi> nay, of a <hi>Stranger,</hi> quickned by no other <hi>Spur</hi> than that of <hi>Honour:</hi> In Heavens Name! what irreconcileable <hi>abſurdities?</hi> what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable <hi>dangers</hi> do men voluntarily run into? was ever, (no 'tis impoſſible) any thing in the world ſo <hi>heteradox</hi> to <hi>reaſon,</hi> nay, to <hi>common-ſence,</hi> as this? for a man to go into the <hi>Field,</hi> to meet he knows not whom, perhaps a <hi>boſom Friend:</hi> to fight in juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of he knows not what, it may be giving the <hi>Lye:</hi> to loſe his life in <hi>Complezance,</hi> he knows not how: poſſibly by being over-power'd by two or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99667:15"/>three This is an <hi>Intreague,</hi> that for my Soul I cannot comprehend: A <hi>Gordian knot</hi> ſo interwoven, and complicated, that were <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf alive, it would <hi>nonplus</hi> both him and his Sword. What can be 'th Riddle of this! Do men propoſe ſafety to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by electing <hi>Seconds?</hi> If they do, I deny their <hi>Major.</hi> For if either of the Seconds fall, I ſuppoſe (pardon me if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>err) he that ſlew him, may if he pleaſe, return to the aſſiſtance of his <hi>own principal,</hi> and then there are two againſt one. So that one choſen for a ſafe guard, may become either through his want of skill, or good luck, deſtructive to the Perſon for whom he Engages. But there is yet a a greater inconvenience that attends this <hi>Folly:</hi> For when only two fight, 'tis very poſſible that ſatisfaction may be had without the Death of either. But in this caſe where four or ſix engage, 'tis not to be imagined they ſhall all eſcape, and all Men know that the Death of either, renders all parties concerned as obnoxious to the <hi>Law,</hi> as if each were the man that had given him his mortal wound. In my apprehenſion, ſuch undertakers ſeem to have no other <hi>Plot,</hi> than by ſetting themſelves beyond the bounds of ſafety, to let the World know how little
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99667:16"/>they fear <hi>Death:</hi> And does not every <hi>fellow</hi> that is poſſeſt with <hi>Deſpair,</hi> a <hi>Frenzy,</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> or what you will call it, while he <hi>Stabs, Hangs,</hi> or <hi>Drowns</hi> himſelf, deſerve to be enrolled among theſe <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> of Honour, upon the ſame account? I think he does.</p>
            <p>But to what purpoſe do I argue, when even mens <hi>own inclinations</hi> ſuperſede my <hi>reaſonings.</hi> In this caſe men by a <hi>Diabolical</hi> kind of <hi>infatuation, do</hi> that which they <hi>would not,</hi> and confute the <hi>ſucceſsion</hi> of <hi>Action</hi> and <hi>Election.</hi> 'Tis in vain to diſwade a man from an enterprize, when he ſays himſelf,
<q>
                  <l>—Video meliora probo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deteriora ſequor.—</l>
               </q> Nor can I rationally expect ſuch mens compliance with <hi>my arguments,</hi> who cannot be obedient to their <hi>own wills.</hi> I dare appeal to any Man, whether he ever went into the <hi>Field</hi> (to fight a <hi>Duel</hi> I mean) <hi>unconcernedly:</hi> or having ſlain his <hi>adverſary,</hi> returned joyfully. And can this be <hi>true Honour</hi> that has <hi>Regret</hi> for its <hi>Companion,</hi> and <hi>Sorrow</hi> for its <hi>Lackey?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having gone ſo far, as to decry <hi>Duel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and to declare it as my opinion, that a <hi>wounded reputation</hi> is not to be cured by <hi>weapon-ſalve:</hi> It may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99667:16"/>be expected that I ſhould propoſe ſome more <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable</hi> way for the ſatisfaction of a <hi>Perſon injured</hi> in his <hi>good Name,</hi> by the reproaches of another.</p>
            <p>But I conceive it improper to prepare <hi>Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> before a Patient is ſatisfied that he is diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered: and Rude, thus to endeavour to <hi>drench</hi> him into Health againſt his Will; and take away the edge of that, which he calls a <hi>good ſtomach,</hi> when, indeed, it is <hi>appetitus caninus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the attempt I have made, chance to work any way upon the Spirits of the <hi>Duellist,</hi> ſo as to bring him to himſelf, out of thoſe <hi>raving fits,</hi> in which there is no coming <hi>neer him,</hi> without <hi>danger;</hi> I have thoſe <hi>Lenitives</hi> in ſtore, that will not (I hope) prove ſo <hi>Ganenically nauſeating,</hi> but that he may down with them: nor ſo <hi>Spirituous,</hi> and <hi>Chimical,</hi> but that he may take them ſafely: ſuch as I dare ſay, will be conducing to <hi>long Life,</hi> and effect the <hi>Cure</hi> (as the <hi>Quack</hi>'s Bill runs) without <hi>hindrance</hi> of <hi>buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or <hi>loſs</hi> of <hi>reputation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this firſt <hi>Eſsay</hi> find the leaſt of a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reception among Men, I ſhall adventure upon a ſecond endeavour, to ſhew how in moſt caſes a Man's <hi>Honour</hi> may be <hi>preſerv'd</hi> without <hi>Duels:</hi> and remove the <hi>Tyranical impoſition</hi> of ſitting at a Feaſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99667:17"/>with a <hi>Sword</hi> hanging over our heads, faſtned only by a hair. Yet leaſt I ſhould never meet with this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement; I only ſay in general, he that will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his <hi>Honour</hi> entire, and his <hi>Reputation</hi> ſound; let him be morally good; let him behave himſelf ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively towards his Superiours, Valliantly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Enemies, Civilly towards his Equals, and Courteouſly towards his Inferiours; ſuch a Deportment as this will prove a <hi>gag</hi> to <hi>Malice,</hi> and a <hi>ſcourge</hi> to <hi>Slander:</hi> and whoſoever is of this temper, will ſoon find that the ſatisfaction a man gives to the World, by his own life, is better than that which he reaps to himſelf by another Man's Death.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
